Guide to the Victor H. Paltsits Papers 1825–1952 (bulk, circa 1890–1952) MS 477.1
New-York Historical Society
Victor H. Paltsits papers
1825–1952 (bulk, circa 1890–1952)
New-York Historical Society
Paltsits, Victor Hugo, 1867–1952.
MS 477.1
37 Linear feet in 73 boxes (38 document boxes, 20 half document boxes, 12 record cartons, 3 flat boxes).
Correspondence, research and subject files, diaries, scrapbooks, and publications of librarian and historian Victor Hugo Paltsits (1867–1952). Dr. Paltsits was associated with the New York Public Library from its inception in 1895 (having been employed by its predecessor, the Lenox Library, since 1888). He served as keeper of manuscripts and chief of NYPL's American History division until his retirement in 1941. A tireless bibliographer, Paltsits was hailed as an "unnamed partner in a thousand works that have advanced the learning of this country and the world." The collection includes a substantial number of his published writings, on topics reflecting a wide interest, such as the founding of New Amsterdam, the history of Pemaquid (now Bristol), Maine, and the early American poet Joseph Rodman Drake (1795–1820). Also documented is Paltsits's tenure as New York State Historian (1907–1911), during when the State Capitol Building at Albany, which then housed the State Library, suffered a devastating fire.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Dr. Victor H. Paltsits, 14 March 1953.
Arrangement
The Victor H. Paltsits Papers are organized in five series:
Series I.
Correspondence, 1890s–1952
Series II.
Research and subject files, 1888–1952
Series III.
Diaries, 1891–1949
Series IV.
Scrapbooks, 1894–1944
Series V.
Publications, 1825–1951
The collection is in 73 boxes numbered 1 through 25-A and 25-B through 72.
Biographical Note
Librarian, bibliographer, and historian Victor Hugo Paltsits (1867–1952) was born in New York City on 12 July 1867 to William Thomas and Sidonia Ida (Loose) Paltsits. His father, a native of Hungary, was the son of a royal banker and prominent merchant, who owned the largest sugar warehouse in Budapest. Victor Paltsits received his early education at public and private schools in New York, and while in high school studied German, Latin, Greek, French, and Spanish, the latter under Cuban poet José Martí (1853–1895). He later delved into Coptic and Egyptian hieroglyphics at Columbia University, and took a four-year scientific course at Cooper Institute.
In 1888 Paltsits began working as a custodian of the art gallery in the Lenox Library, on Fifth Avenue at 70th Street, where he began making notes on the paintings in his care as a means of personal study, and in order to answer the queries of visitors. Under the tutelage of library head Wilberforce Eames (1855–1937), the "Dean of American Bibliographers," Paltsits made his first attempts at bibliographic description. He was promoted to assistant librarian in the Lenox reading room in 1890, and to sub-librarian in 1893. In 1895 the Lenox Library became part of the New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations. Paltsits's title once again became assistant librarian, but he had charge of the Lenox reading rooms, where he performed the function of chief reference librarian.
Victor Paltsits served as New York State Historian in 1907–1911, during which time he produced editions of Minutes of the Commissioners for Detecting and Defeating Conspiracies in the State of New York (1909–10) and Minutes of the Executive Council of the Province of New York: Administration of Francis Lovelace, 1668-1673(1910). In Albany Paltsits lobbied the State Legislature—unsuccessfully—to create a unified system of archival records retention. In 1911 he began a seventeen-year association with I. N. Phelps Stokes, providing research and advice for his seminal compilation, The Iconography of Manhattan Island.
At the New York Public Library—now in its headquarters at Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street—Paltsits took charge of the manuscript division beginning in 1914 (under the title "keeper of manuscripts") and of the American History division in 1916, retaining both positions until his retirement in 1941. Although he controlled millions of manuscripts, Paltsits was never an archivist. Nevertheless, he was a founding member of the Society of American Archivists, and his 1912 paper, "Plan and Scope for a Manual of Archival Economy for the Use of American Archivists," has led some to consider him the father of modern archival practice.
The list of works of bibliography, biography, and scholarship produced by Paltsits during his career, not to mention those to which he contributed in his official capacities, is too long to recount. Of note are his Bibliography of the Separate & Collected Works of Philip Freneau, Together with an Account of His Newspaper (1903), Papers and Proceedings of the Drake Memorial Celebration, May 29, 1915, Together with a Bibliography of the Writings of Dr. Joseph Rodman Drake (1919), and Narrative of American Voyages and Travels of Captain William Owen, R.N., and Settlement of the Island of Campobello in the Bay of Fundy, 1766–1771 (1942).
Victor Paltsits married Anne Müller (1871–1944) in 1891. They had two children: Florence and Victor John Paltsits. Anne Paltsits died, tragically, a few days after the couple moved into a new home. Paltsits died on 3 October 1952, aged eighty-five, and was buried in Woodlawn Cemetery, in the Bronx.
[For more on Paltsits, see his entries in The National Cyclopædia of American Biography, vol. 17, pp. 198–99, and Who Was Who in America, vol. 3, p. 663. Box 63 of the present collection contains some thirty-seven works written or edited by Paltsits. Fuller bibliographies are provided by the aforementioned citations.]
Related Materials
In addition to a number of published works and some smaller, related archival collections, which may be found through BobCat, the library's online catalog, the New-York Historical Society holds two larger collections assembled by Paltsits:
1) Paltsits Collection--Ulster County, New York, 1643-1829, MS 477.
2) Victor H. Paltsits manuscript collection, ca. 1703 - ca. 1928, MS 478.
Scope and Contents
The Victor H. Paltsits Papers include a mixture of professional and personal correspondence (1890s–1952) with colleagues such as historian Charles McLean Andrews (1863–1943), librarian and bibliographer George Watson Cole (1850–1939), historian and novelist Edward Eggleston (1837–1902), Canadian historian William Francis Ganong (1864–1941), lawyer and historian William Nelson (1837–1914), Poe biographer Mary E. Phillips (1857–1945), librarian and historical writer Reuben Gold Thwaites (1853–1913), and the publishers Burrows Brothers Co.
The collection also includes research and subject files reflecting Paltsits's various interests and activities, from his earliest days as an employee of the Lenox Library (as documented in a commonplace book of 1888–1889), his work as critical advisor on historical illustration for Elroy M. Avery's "A History of the United States and its People, From Their Earliest Records to the Present Time" (published by Burrows Brothers, 1904–1910), his involvement with the Public Archives Commission of the American Historical Association (1908–1924), his tenure as New York State Historian (1907–1911), during when he lobbied the State Legislature unsuccessfully for the creation of a unified archival system.
Paltsits's diaries (1891–1949) record his frequent research trips and accompanying expenditures. His scrapbooks (1894–1944) are largely personal in content, recording the honorary doctorates he received from Brown University (1936) and Rutgers University (1938), his retirement from the New York Public Library (1941), and the sudden death of his wife, Anne (Müller) Paltsits (1944), who passed away a few days after the couple moved into a new home.
Rounding out the collection are (roughly) thirty-seven publications by Paltsits on topics such as Herman Melville, the works of Philip Freneau, and America's first newspaper. These are followed by five boxes of books and periodical offprints by various authors, some kept by Paltsits from his student days, but many of them written by colleagues and research acquaintances who inscribed their works to Paltsits.
Bibliographies.; Bio-bibliographies.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Newspaper clippings.; Pamphlets.; Research notes.; Scrapbooks.; American newspapers -- History.; American poetry -- Hudson River Valley (N.Y. and N.J.) -- 1783-1850.; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Archives -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bibliography.; Book collectors -- United States.; Booksellers and bookselling -- United States.; Coptic language.; Egyptian language.; Fires -- New York (State) -- Albany.; Hieroglyphics.; Judges -- New York (State) -- Biography.; Library science -- Terminology.; Manuscripts -- United States.; Printers -- United States.; Progressive Party (U.S.: 1912); Publishers and publishing.; Campobello Island (N.B.) -- History.; Jamaica (New York, N.Y.) -- History.; New York (State) -- Description and travel.; New York (State) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Pemaquid (Me.) -- History.; United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1754-1763 -- Personal Narratives.; United States -- History -- King George's War, 1744-1748.; Andrews, Charles McLean, 1863-1943.; Avery, Elroy McKendree, 1844-1935.; Cole, George Watson, 1850-1939.; Drake, Joseph Rodman, 1795-1820 -- Anniversaries, etc.; Eggleston, Edward, 1837-1902.; Freneau, Philip Morin, 1752-1832.; Ganong, William Francis, 1864-1941.; Lenox, James, 1800-1880.; Martí, José, 1853-1895.; Melville, Herman, 1819-1891.; Nelson, William, 1847-1914.; Owen, William, 1738?-1778.; Paltsits, Victor Hugo, 1867–1952.; Phillips, Mary Elizabeth, 1857-1945.; Porter, Augustus, 1769-1849.; Pote, William, approximately 1766-1847.; Rogers, Robert, 1731-1795.; Talbot, Silas, 1751-1813.; Thacher, John Boyd, 1847-1909.; Thwaites, R. G. (Reuben Gold), 1853-1913.; American Historical Association. Public Archives Commission.; Burrows Brothers Company.; Lenox Library.; New York Public Library. Manuscript Division.; New York State Capitol (Albany, N.Y.) -- Fire, 1911.
- Series I. Correspondence, 1890s–1952
  Arrangement
  Boxes are listed in the order they were stored on the shelves. Items lacking dates in the container list were not inspected at the time the collection was prepared for offsite storage (November-December 2020).
  - Correspondence (individually cataloged) (Offsite-box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1890s–1900s (Offsite-box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The content of this box remains in its original unprocessed state and requires up to two (2) business days for preparation before patron use, in addition to the two (2) to five (5) business days required for offsite delivery. Requests for multiple boxes with this restriction should allow for up to two (2) business days per box.
  - Correspondence, 1890s–1900s (Offsite-box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Offsite-box 4)
  - Correspondence [box 1 of 2], 1910s–1920s (Offsite-box 5)
  - Correspondence [box 2 of 2], 1910s–1920s (Offsite-box 6)
  - Correspondence [box 1 of 2], 1920s–1930s (Offsite-box 7)
  - Correspondence [box 2 of 2], 1920s–1930s (Offsite-box 8)
  - Correspondence [box 1 of 2], 1930s–1940s (Offsite-box 9)
  - Correspondence [box 2 of 2], 1930s–1940s (Offsite-box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1940s (Offsite-box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1940s–1950s (Offsite-box 12)
  - Correspondence. Charles McLean Andrews, George Watson Cole, Reuben Gold Thwaites (Offsite-box 13)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) [box 1 of 2] (Offsite-box 14)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) [box 2 of 2] (Offsite-box 15)
  - Correspondence. Various publishers and miscellaneous (Offsite-box 16)
  - Correspondence. National Progressive Party (1912), National Peace Conference (1909), American Health League (1908), National Archives, 1908–1912 (Offsite-box 17)
  - Correspondence. Burrows Bros. Co. (Offsite-box 18)
  - Correspondence. William F. Ganong (Offsite-box 19)
  - Correspondence. Edward Eggleston, William Nelson (Offsite-box 20)
  - Correspondence. H. C. Fitz Randolph, Charlotte Hoadley, Victor Hugo Duras (Offsite-box 21)
  - Correspondence. Poe correspondence with Mary Phillips (Offsite-box 22)
- Series II. Research and subject files, 1888–1952
  - Subseries II.A. Research and subject files sorted circa 1953
    - Public Archives Commission of the American Historical Association [box 1 of 4], [1908–1924] (Offsite-box 23)
      Scope and Contents
      Paltsits was a member of the Public Archives Commission of the American Historical Association from 1908 to 1924, and its chairman from 1911 to 1922.
    - Public Archives Commission of the American Historical Association [box 2 of 4], [1908–1924] (Offsite-box 24)
    - Public Archives Commission of the American Historical Association [box 3 of 4], [1908–1924] (Offsite-box 25-A)
    - Public Archives Commission of the American Historical Association [box 4 of 4], [1908–1924] (Offsite-box 25-B)
    - Bibliography (French and Indian War) (Offsite-box 26)
    - Dictionary of American Biography; Avery's "History of the United States"; Stokes's "Iconography of Manhattan Island" (Offsite-box 27)
    - Personal (Offsite-box 28)
    - National Society of Autograph Collectors (Offsite-box 29)
    - Miscellaneous addresses, monographs, etc. (Offsite-box 30)
    - Miscellaneous addresses (Offsite-box 31)
    - Lenox (Offsite-box 32)
    - Lenox (Offsite-box 33)
    - Champlain (Offsite-box 34)
    - Champlain (Offsite-box 35)
    - Bills, etc., from booksellers, publishers, etc. to V. H. Paltsits, before 1908 (Offsite-box 36)
    - Brick Row Book Shop, Swann's (Offsite-box 37)
    - Poe [crossed out], Bronx-Drake, Edison (Offsite-box 38)
    - Miscellaneous (Offsite-box 39)
    - Miscellaneous (Offsite-box 40)
    - Notes, etc. Henry Hudson, John Boyd Thacher, T. J. Frelinghuysen, Augustus Porter, Nathan Hale, Francis Lewis, Silas Talbot (Offsite-box 41)
      Material likely pertaining to Paltsits's publications "Judge Augustus Porter, Pioneer of Niagara Falls, With an Account of His Business Day Book of 1818 to 1822" (1937) and "The Honorable John Boyd Thacher, Man of Versatility" (1951). For copies, see box 63.
    - Notes, etc. Bunyan's Pilgrim's Progress, Pemaquid, Gyles (Offsite-box 42)
      Material likely pertaining to Paltsits's publications "The Captivity of John Gyles, 1689–1698" (1900) and "The Depredation at Pemaquid in August, 1689, and Events That Led Up To It" (1905). For copies, see box 63.
    - Notes, etc. Printers and printing (Offsite-box 43)
    - Notes, etc. Books and bibliography (Offsite-box 44)
    - Notes, etc. New York (Offsite-box 45)
    - Notes, etc. Bible, Jesuit Relations, etc. (Offsite-box 46)
    - Canada (William F. Ganong) [box 1 of 2] (Offsite-box 47)
    - Canada (William F. Ganong) [box 2 of 2] (Offsite-box 48)
    - Journal of William Pote (Offsite-box 49)
      Material likely pertaining to Paltsits's edition of "The Journal of Capt. William Pote, Jr. 1745–1747" (1896). Pote was a British surveyor and ship captain who left a narrative of his captivity among the Wabanaki Confederacy during King George's War.
    - Owen's Journal (Offsite-box 50)
      Material likely pertaining to Paltsits's publication "Narrative of American Voyages and Travels of Captain William Owen, R.N., and Settlement of the Island of Campobello in the Bay of Fundy, 1766–1771" (1942), first serialized in the Bulletin of the New York public Library, February-October 1931. For copies, see box 63.
    - State Library Fire, 1911 (Offsite-box 51)
      On 29 March 1911, during Paltsits's tenure as New York State Historian, the New York State Capitol building, which then housed the State Library, suffered a devastating fire which consumed or damaged countless unique documents.
    - State Historian [box 1 of 6], [1907–1911] (Offsite-box 52)
      Material from Paltsits's tenure as New York State Historian during 1907–1911.
    - State Historian [box 2 of 6], [1907–1911] (Offsite-box 53)
    - State Historian [box 3 of 6], [1907–1911] (Offsite-box 54)
    - State Historian [box 4 of 6], [1907–1911] (Offsite-box 55)
    - State Historian [box 5 of 6], [1907–1911] (Offsite-box 56)
    - State Historian [box 6 of 6], [1907–1911] (Offsite-box 57)
  - Subseries II.B. Research and subject files processed 2020
    Items are listed alphabetically by title or topic.
    - American Historical Association, 1949 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 1)
    - American Library Institute, 1917–1938 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 2)
    - Ancient writing [1 notebook], undated (Offsite-box 58, Folder 3)
    - Appleton's Cyclopædia of American Biography, 1898, 1936 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 4)
    - Autograph collectors [3 notebooks], undated (Offsite-box 58, Folder 5)
    - Avery's "History of the United States." Illustrations, etc. [7 folders], circa 1900–1910 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 6–12)
      Paltsits served as critical advisor on historical illustration for Elroy M. Avery's "A history of the United States and its people, from their earliest records to the present time" (1904–1910). Only seven volumes of a projected sixteen were published. As described by Paltsits: "These copy note-books [in folders 6–10] relate to the researches made for illustrating Elroy M. Avery's History of the U.S. published by the Burrows Bros. Co. of Cleveland. Made on tours from original research and valuable data. VHP."
    - Canada notes, undated (Offsite-box 58, Folder 13)
    - Chemical rejuvenation of faded ink, 1932–1935 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 14)
    - Commonplace book, 1888–1889 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 15)
      As described by Paltsits: "A commonplace book that I began in 1888, my first year in the Lenox Library, Fifth Avenue and 70th to 71st Streets, New York City. It was at that time that I began my interest in bibliography, in learning to read proof, and in general cultural reading. It was from Dr. S. Austin Allibone, then the Lenox Librarian, that I was lent Theodore L. DeVinne's 'History of the Invention of Printing,' which I read carefully through, and read through again, and partly a third time. I was also during the summer months of 1889, when the Library was closed, sitting beside Wilberforce Eames, in the south reading room, and got from him inspiration to attempt correct bibliographical description, of which the inserted bibliographical descriptions are the evidence. Victo H. Paltsits, Sept. 22, 1945."
    - Drake, Joseph Rodman, circa 1910–1947 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 16)
    - Eames, Dr. Wilberforce, 1931 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 17)
    - Egyptian language (Coptic and hieroglyphics) [5 folders], 1894–1942 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 18–22)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Albany, New York, 1909 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 1)
      As described by Paltsits: "Materials gathered toward a history of the First Presbyterian Church of Albany in May, 1909, by Victor Hugo Paltsits, State Historian."
    - Flatlands, Brooklyn, New York, 1922–1929 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 2)
    - Forged Columbus letter, before 1951 August 30 (Offsite-box 70 (flat))
      As described by Paltsits: "Should I not live to work this material into a volume on Forged Columbus Letter of his first voyage, it is my wish that this bundle go to the New-York Historical Society, Central Park West, to be kept there with my other Papers, etc. Victor H. Paltsits, Aug. 30, 1951."
    - Fort George (New York) [notebook], 1890 May (Offsite-box 59, Folder 3)
      As described by Paltsits: "Relation de la prise du Fort Georges, ou Guillaume-Henry. [A Transcript]."
    - French and Indian War [notebook], undated (Offsite-box 59, Folder 4)
      As described by Paltsits: "The Chalmers Papers. Transcripts of Such Portions as Relate to the French and Indian War. From 'Papers Relating to Virginia.' Lettered 'Vol. II. 1689-1770' in the New York Public Library, Copied by Victor Hugo Paltsits."
    - Freneau, Philip, 1902–1946 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 5)
      Material pertaining to Paltsits's "Bibliography of the Separate & Collected Works of Philip Freneau, Together with an Account of His Newspaper" (1903).
    - Hanna, Charles A. Reviews of "Historical collections of Harrison County, in the state of Ohio", 1901 March 21 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 6)
    - Hughes, Charles Evans. Funeral and obituary tributes, 1948 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 7)
    - Illustrations. Military uniforms—Austrian, undated (Offsite-box 59, Folder 8)
    - Illustrations. Military uniforms—French [2 folders], undated (Offsite-box 59, Folder 9–10)
    - Illustrations. Military uniforms—Prussian, undated (Offsite-box 59, Folder 11)
    - Illustrations. Theatrical, undated (Offsite-box 59, Folder 12)
    - Jefferson, Dr. Charles E., 1928–1937 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 13)
    - Lenox Collection paintings, 1888 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 14)
      Notebook, as described by Paltsits: "The paintings here described were part of the art in the James Lenox collection, of the Lenox Library, Fifth Ave. 70–71 Sts., New York, in 1888, the year I began service there as a custodian in the art gallery on the second floor, where I remained some two years. These notes were made as a means of personal study, in order to answer public inquiry, or to otherwise interest visitors to the gallery. Victor Hugo Paltsits."
    - Martí, José [4 folders], 1889–1952 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 15–18)
      Paltsits studied high school Spanish under Cuban poet and national hero José Martí (1853–1895), who taught in New York in the early 1890s. See Paltsits's reminiscences of Martí in folder 15.
    - Martí, José [2 books], 1909, 1942 (Offsite-box 72)
      • Martí Nuestra América, vol. VII (1909)
      • Martí: Prólogo y selección de Mauricio Magdaleno (1942)
    - Miscellaneous notes, ephemera, etc., circa 1900–1951 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 1)
    - National Archives, 1935–1944 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, circa 1900–1952 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 3)
    - Notebooks [3 in 1 folder], undated (Offsite-box 60, Folder 4)
      As described by Paltsits: "These note books contain references to important, mostly unknown, matters in N.Y. 18th century history, on bookbinders, Robert Rogers, early libraries, booksellers, etc., etc. VHP."
    - Personal library. Short-title list, before 1900 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 5)
      As described by Paltsits: "This is a short-title list of Books, etc. that I owned about the end of the 19th century. Those relating to the last inter-colonial war, the fourth French and Indian War, ending by the Treaty of 1763, I sold as a lot to the Pequot Library at Southport, Conn., including more than there are here, for $250!"
    - Personal library. Anderson Galleries, "Catalogue of Books on American Family History, the Fine Arts, Sets of Standard Authors, Rare Pamphlets, etc., etc.", 1908 March 2-3 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 6)
      As described by Paltsits: "Report of items sold belonging to Victor H. Paltsits. Those priced are the ones. A slaughter!"
    - Personal library. "Books from library. Auction inventory", 1911 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 7)
    - Personal library. "My books sold by Anderson Galleries" (3 volumes), 1915 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 8)
    - Personal library. "My personal record. Books of an Old Librarian. Part 3", 1942 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 9)
    - Personal library. "Various lists of the sale, deposit, etc. of my books at auction, with Brick Row Book Shop, L. C. Harper, and Queens Borough Public Library", 1945 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 10)
    - Personal library. Bibliographic entry cards, undated (Offsite-box 61, Enclosure D)
    - Publick Occurrences, circa 1930 (Offsite-box 60, Folder 11)
      Manuscript drafts of Paltsits's 1950 article "New Light on 'Publick Occurrences,' America's First Newspaper."